In this video, I'm going to demonstrate
some of the structural formatting tools
that you can use to enhance the meaning
and appearance of your presentation.
As you can see, the presentation that I
have on screen at the moment contains four
slides and there is no real definition
to the layout and the different sections
within each of the slides other than
having two images on the title slide.
So when you're creating a presentation,
the first thing you need to do is to
make sure that you select the right
layout for the slide that you're
going to include the content in.
So for example, on slide
one, this is a title slide.
So if I just click on that and go
to the home tab and then select
a slide layout button, I can
see that that is a title slide.
For the second one, I have
used a two content slide.
For the third slide, it
is a title and content.
And for the fourth slide again,
it is a title and content.
So it is important that you try and
select the correct layout for the
information that you need to include.
However, it may be a case at a later
point in the design and development
of your presentation that you
wish to change the slide layout.
So for example, on slide three, at
the moment, I have some information
in here that may be enhanced
by the inclusion of a chart.
So at this point, what I'd need to do is
to change the actual layout of the slide.
So now that  I've got the slide
highlighted, if I go up to the
layout and then selected two content
that will automatically change.
So as you can see, it has compressed
the information that was already on
the slide to the left, which that will
then allow me to add the different
type of information to the right.
So I could then select chart or
a table or some other type of
information and add that to the slide.
So I'll just undo that.
There also may be occasions where you
may need to change the slide order.
So when you're doing a presentation,
you may think that slide three will
be better as slide four, slide five
or slide six and so on and so forth.
It's quite straightforward
within PowerPoint to change
the order of the slides.
All you would need to do is as
an example, I've selected slide
two, and I want to change that.
So it'll change places with
slide three, just click and
hold and then drag that down.
And again, if I wanted to change slide
four to slide three, just click and hold
and drag it to where I wish it to be.
I can then change them back and I have
the original order presented again.
As you can see the slides at the
moment are quite plain and have
a white background, there's text
there, but there is no definition.
The information hasn't
been broken up in any way.
One of the other tools that you can
use is you can break each section down.
So for example, I'm going to use the
business growth slide to demonstrate this.
So I have the title section here.
So I click on the title,
the box appears around it.
So I can then add a border to that.
And I'm just going to
select a plain black border.
And again, for the information to the
left of the chart, I will select a border.
And for the chart, I'll do exactly the
same, select a border around the chart.
So, as you can see, that has
now started to define the
information within this slide.
I can also take that one step
further and if highlight that
I can actually add a fill.
So I can select a color
to fill the background.
That's quite dramatic.
I think I'll go for that shade there,
again, I could do this same shade so, the
last shade selected will automatically
be the one by default that you can
select, but again, drop down, but I'll
stick with the shade that I went with.
But for the chart, all I'm
going to do is define that by,
I may make the border thicker.
So again, the border was quite thin
so I can select weight and then I can
put a thicker border around the chart.
So as you can see, that has
slowly broken that information up.
So each section has got
its own defined area.
When creating presentations,
there may also be occasions where
you need to hide certain slides.
So for example, it could be a presentation
that has been presented to members
of the staff and also managers within
an organization, but rather than have
two different presentations, you've
created one that has additional
information in for the managers.
And when you present that to
the staff, you need to make sure
that they can't see those slides.
So quite simply you can hide the
slides within the presentation.
And to do that, all you would do is
highlight the slide that you wish to hide.
Right click and then select hide slide.
So when that was presented slide two, as
it has a strike through there, you would
see that that would not be displayed.
So with, in the presentation, it
goes slide one and then jump straight
to slide three and slide four.
And then when you decide that you need to
present that with all of the slideshow,
you would simply right click again.
Select hide slide, and that will take
the strike-through away from the number.
So in the presentation, it
would go one, two, three, and
four with no slides omitted.
As with Word, you also have the
opportunity to use headers and
footers and within PowerPoint to
access the headers and footers, you
would simply go to the insert tab
and then select headers and footers.
And it may be a case that you wish to
put the date and time in and have that
updated automatically, or it could be
fixed so if I select date and time.
So whenever the presentation is
displayed, it would automatically
change the date to that date that it was
presented, or you could have it fixed.
So if you wanted to have it fixed so it
displayed the date, when the presentation
was created, you would select that
option, you can also select slide number.
And if you look along the right and
the preview pane, it's showing you
exactly where that information would be.
Additionally, you may also
wish to have the footer active.
So that could be a case of you maybe
need to put the, the company name in
there or the author of the presentation.
So if I select that, now I have the option
to either select it so it doesn't show
on the title slide but I want it to show
on every slide and I can apply that, but
it will only apply it to that one slide.
Alternatively, I can select apply
to all, and that will apply that
to every slide in the presentation.
So if I select that now, as you
can see, it has applied that
to each of the four slides.
Primarily most slides within a
presentation are in landscape format.
And most presentations are
presented in landscape format.
However, there may be occasions where
you need to change it to portrait format.
Now, within portrait format, one of
the things you have to be aware of
is that when you change one slide to
portrait, unlike Word, where you could
have one page in landscape, one page in
portrait and other page in landscape,
within PowerPoint, if you change the
orientation of one slide, it will change
the orientation of all the slides.
So just to demonstrate that if I
have the title slide selected, and
then I need to go to the design tab.
And on the design tab select slide
size and at the moment you've got
standard or widescreen, but you would
need to select custom slide size.
And from there you would
need to select portrait.
So if I click portrait and
hit OK, you get two options.
So you can either maximize
the information or ensure fit.
If you select maximize, it would basically
change the page orientation, but the
information within won't change, So if
I do that now, select, maximize, and
then select that, as you can see, that
isn't really fit for purpose because
it's changed the slides to portrait, but
the information is still in landscape.
So if I just undo that and again,
go back to the slide size, custom
slide fit, select portrait, select
OK, but this time select ensure fit.
As you can see that has then ensured that
the information does fit on the slide.